Hallucinations are one of the biggest
problems with modern language models.
But why exactly they hallucinate and is
it possible to mitigate those? I think
we finally have an answer. So there is a
very interesting paper from OpenAI
titled why language models hallucinate.
They argue that the main reason of
hallucinations is how we train and
evaluate these language models. So in
here they say hallucinations need not be
mysterious. They originate simply as
errors in binary classification.
If incorrect statements can't be
distinguished from facts, then
hallucinations in pre-trained language
models will arise through natural
statistical pressures. Now, don't worry
if this does not make sense. I'm going
to break it down and we're going to see
why this exactly happens. For this, we
will first need to understand how
language model works. So commonly we say
that language models are next word
predictors but I would argue they are a
lot more than that. So here's a very
quick demo that I put together with help
of claude. Now there are usually two
steps. One is pre-training and the other
one is postraining. We have a massive
text data set. We pass this through a
large language model and it will
recognize patterns in the data and based
on the distribution of tokens, it's
going to make next word prediction. But
I would argue it does a lot more. So for
example, if you were to ask something
like this in Paris, the capital of
France, the primary language spoken is
the prediction should be French if you
have a pre-trained model. But in order
to make that prediction, it's not only
just looking at the distribution of
words. The model needs to understand
grammar also it needs to be able to have
long distance context through self
attention. So for example, it needs to
keep track of Paris uh its relationship
to France and then the language the user
is asking about. Also it needs to have
word knowledge. So it needs to know that
Paris is in France and then French is
the primary spoken language in there and
then it also should be able to uh filter
any distractors in the language. Now
having said that it still needs to
predict the next word. So it will come
up with a probability distribution of
what the next word prediction should
look like and that's where the main
issue comes into play. So [snorts] even
if the model does not have knowledge
about a certain topic, it's going to
pick a word based on the distribution
that it has seen. So sometimes you're
going to see that the model will
generate answers which are incorrect but
it's extremely confident in those
answers and that's where hallucinations
come from. Their main argument is that
hallucinations persist because
the evaluation mechanism that is used
today encourages generating answers
rather than abstinence. So in here they
say hallucinations persist partly
because current evaluation methods set
the wrong incentives. While evaluations
themselves do not directly cause
hallucinations, most evaluations measure
model performance in a way that
encourages guessing rather than honesty
about uncertaintity. So in most training
paradigms, we use cross entropy which is
the negative log of the probability of
correct prediction. So essentially you
can convert this into a binary
classification problem. As a result,
either the model can correctly predict
the next token or incorrectly predict
the next token. Now, the model doesn't
really have another option and that's
why it incentivize just guessing. So,
here they say if you do not know the
answer but take a wild guess, you might
get lucky and be right. Leaving it blank
guarantees a zero. In the same way when
models are graded only on accuracy the
percentage of questions they get exactly
right they are encouraged to guess
rather than say I don't know now that's
where we need to have a different type
of evaluation when we are training these
models so they argue that for questions
where there is a single right answer one
can consider three categories of
responses one is going to be accurate
responses the second will be errors and
third is abstinence where the model does
not hazard a guess. Now in order to
incentivize abstinence you will have to
change the reward function and OpenAI is
working on models where uh rather than
just generating an answer the model is
encouraged more to ask uh clarifying or
follow-up questions. Now GBT5 compared
to the previous versions have
drastically lower hallucination rates
and in some cases uh it's less than 1%
but still hallucinations do occur. They
also argue that apart from uh training
the evaluations on benchmarks also
incentivize hallucinations. So they say
the accuracy on the scoreboards dominate
leaderboards and model cards, motivating
developers to build models that guess
rather than hold back. And accuracy
being just binary classification where
the model is encouraged to guess rather
than get a zero on a question. That is
one reason why even as the models get
more advanced they can still hallucinate
confidently giving wrong answers instead
of acknowledging uncertaintity. So we
will have actually need to change the
way we uh do our benchmarking as well.
So there are two different components uh
if we want to reduce hallucination.
[clears throat] First when it comes to
training we need to change uh the reward
function for training mechanisms and in
the second part we also need to work on
the leaderboards or scoreboards when we
are comparing different models. So here
they say penalizing confident errors
more than you penalize uncertaintity and
give partial credit for appropriate
expression of uncertaintity. This idea
is not new. Some standardized tests have
long used variation of negative marking
for wrong answers or partial credit for
leaving questions blanks to discourage
blind guessings. We will have to come up
with a very similar mechanism for LLMs
as well. But that's more on the training
side. Then they talk about uh it's not
enough to add a few new uncertaintity
aware tests on the side. The widely used
accuracy based evolves need to be
updated so that their scoring
discourages guessing. If the main
scoreboards keep rewarding lucky
guesses, models will keep learning to
guess. In fact, they mean that the model
creators are going to uh make the models
so that they keep guessing. Now, fixing
scoreboards can broaden adoption of
hallucination reduction techniques. both
newly developed and those from prior
research. Next, we're going to look at
some interesting observations from their
paper. Uh so the first one is claim
hallucinations will be eliminated by
improving accuracy because a 100%
accurate model never hallucinates. That
is not correct. So they say accuracy
will never reach 100%. Because
regardless of the model size, search and
reasoning capabilities, some real world
questions are inherently unanswerable.
And if you're trying to achieve 100%
accuracy, they argue that you are
incentivizing hallucinations.
The second claim is hallucinations are
inevitable.
uh they say they're not because language
models can abstain when uncertain and we
can train them so that they actually say
I don't know rather than trying to guess
answers. The next one is avoiding
hallucinations uh require a degree of
intelligence which is exclusively
available to larger models but they
argue that that may not be the case.
Smaller models may actually know their
limits. So for example um their uh
specific example is if asked if um uh
the model is asked about a topic that
the model does not know the smaller
model can actually uh say that it
doesn't know based on um its limited
knowledge. But if a larger model with
more intelligence has knowledge of that
topic uh but not to the extent to which
it can answer the question, it may not
be able to figure out the confidence
level and could still hallucinate. The
next claim is hallucinations are a
mysterious glitch in the modern language
models. Their argument is we understand
the statistical mechanism through which
hallucinations arise and are rewarded in
evaluations. So we know why they occur
and we also know the mechanisms uh in
order to address them. And then to merge
hallucination we just need a good
hallucination evolve. So hallucination
evolves have been published. However, a
good hallucination evolve has little
effect against hundreds of traditional
accuracy based uh evils that penalize
humanity and reward guessing. So instead
all of the primary evol metrics needs to
be reworked to revert expression of
uncertaintity. And that's kind of the
main takeaway. If we just rely on
accuracy based uh metrics for evaluation
of these large language models, we may
never be able to uh eliminate
hallucinations. Let me know what you
think about the topic. I am personally
really interested in understanding large
language models, how they work and why
these interesting phenomenas happen. Do
let me know if you uh are finding this
format useful. Anyways, I hope you found
this video useful. Thanks for watching
and as always, see you in the next one.